<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Ajax</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The XMLHttpRequest method (XHR) allows browsers to communicate with the
    server without requiring a page reload. This method, also known as Ajax
    (Asynchronous JavaScript and XML), allows for web pages that provide rich,
    interactive experiences.</para>

    <para>Ajax requests are triggered by JavaScript code; your code sends a
    request to a URL, and when it receives a response, a callback function can
    be triggered to handle the response. Because the request is asynchronous,
    the rest of your code continues to execute while the request is being
    processed, so it’s imperative that a callback be used to handle the
    response.</para>

    <para>jQuery provides Ajax support that abstracts away painful browser
    differences. It offers both a full-featured <code>$.ajax()</code> method,
    and simple convenience methods such as <code>$.get()</code>,
    <code>$.getScript()</code>, <code>$.getJSON()</code>,
    <code>$.post()</code>, and <code>$().load()</code>.</para>

    <para>Most jQuery applications don’t in fact use XML, despite the name
    “Ajax”; instead, they transport data as plain HTML or JSON (JavaScript
    Object Notation).</para>

    <para>In general, Ajax does not work across domains. Exceptions are
    services that provide JSONP (JSON with Padding) support, which allow
    limited cross-domain functionality.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Key Concepts</title>

    <para>Proper use of Ajax-related jQuery methods requires understanding
    some key concepts first.</para>

    <section>
      <title>GET vs. Post</title>

      <para>The two most common “methods” for sending a request to a server
      are GET and POST. It’s important to understand the proper application of
      each.</para>

      <para>The GET method should be used for non-destructive operations —
      that is, operations where you are only “getting” data from the server,
      not changing data on the server. For example, a query to a search
      service might be a GET request. GET requests may be cached by the
      browser, which can lead to unpredictable behavior if you are not
      expecting it. GET requests generally send all of their data in a query
      string.</para>

      <para>The POST method should be used for destructive operations — that
      is, operations where you are changing data on the server. For example, a
      user saving a blog post should be a POST request. POST requests are
      generally not cached by the browser; a query string can be part of the
      URL, but the data tends to be sent separately as post data.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Data Types</title>

      <para>jQuery generally requires some instruction as to the type of data
      you expect to get back from an Ajax request; in some cases the data type
      is specified by the method name, and in other cases it is provided as
      part of a configuration object. There are several options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>text</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>For transporting simple strings</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>html</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>For transporting blocks of HTML to be placed on the
            page</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>script</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>For adding a new script to the page</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>json</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>For transporting JSON-formatted data, which can include
            strings, arrays, and objects<note>
                <para>As of jQuery 1.4, if the JSON data sent by your server
                isn't properly formatted, the request may fail silently. See
                <link xlink:href="http://json.org">http://json.org</link> for
                details on properly formatting JSON, but as a general rule,
                use built-in language methods for generating JSON on the
                server to avoid syntax issues.</para>
              </note></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>jsonp</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>For transporting JSON data from another domain</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>xml</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>For transporting data in a custom XML schema</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <remark>I am a strong proponent of using the JSON format in most cases,
      as it provides the most flexibility. It is especially useful for sending
      both HTML and data at the same time.</remark>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A is for Asynchronous</title>

      <para>The asynchronicity of Ajax catches many new jQuery users off
      guard. Because Ajax calls are asynchronous by default, the response is
      not immediately available. Responses can only be handled using a
      callback. So, for example, the following code will not work:</para>

	<programlisting>var response;
$.get('foo.php', function(r) { response = r; });
console.log(response); <emphasis>// undefined!</emphasis></programlisting>

      <para>Instead, we need to pass a callback function to our request; this
      callback will run when the request succeeds, at which point we can
      access the data that it returned, if any. <programlisting>$.get('foo.php', function(response) { console.log(response); });</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Same-Origin Policy and JSONP</title>

      <para>In general, Ajax requests are limited to the same protocol (http
      or https), the same port, and the same domain as the page making the
      request. This limitation does not apply to scripts that are loaded via
      jQuery's Ajax methods.</para>

      <para>The other exception is requests targeted at a JSONP service on
      another domain. In the case of JSONP, the provider of the service has
      agreed to respond to your request with a script that can be loaded into
      the page using a <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tag, thus avoiding the
      same-origin limitation; that script will include the data you requested,
      wrapped in a callback function you provide.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ajax and Firebug</title>

      <para>Firebug (or the Webkit Inspector in Chrome or Safari) is an
      invaluable tool for working with Ajax requests. You can see Ajax
      requests as they happen in the Console tab of Firebug (and in the
      Resources &gt; XHR panel of Webkit Inspector), and you can click on a
      request to expand it and see details such as the request headers,
      response headers, response content, and more. If something isn't going
      as expected with an Ajax request, this is the first place to look to
      track down what's wrong.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>jQuery's Ajax-Related Methods</title>

    <para>While jQuery does offer many Ajax-related convenience methods, the
    core <code>$.ajax</code> method is at the heart of all of them, and
    understanding it is imperative. We'll review it first, and then touch
    briefly on the convenience methods.</para>

    <remark>I generally use the $.ajax method and do not use convenience
    methods. As you'll see, it offers features that the convenience methods do
    not, and its syntax is more easily understandable, in my opinion.</remark>

    <section>
      <title>$.ajax</title>

      <para>jQuery’s core <code>$.ajax</code> method is a powerful and
      straightforward way of creating Ajax requests. It takes a configuration
      object that contains all the instructions jQuery requires to complete
      the request. The <code>$.ajax</code> method is particularly valuable
      because it offers the ability to specify both success and failure
      callbacks. Also, its ability to take a configuration object that can be
      defined separately makes it easier to write reusable code. For complete
      documentation of the configuration options, visit <link
      xlink:href="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.ajax/">http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.ajax/</link>.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using the core $.ajax method</title>

        <programlisting>$.ajax({
    // the URL for the request
    url : 'post.php',

    // the data to send 
    // (will be converted to a query string)
    data : { id : 123 },

    // whether this is a POST or GET request
    type : 'GET',

    // the type of data we expect back
    dataType : 'json',

    // code to run if the request succeeds;
    // the response is passed to the function
    success : function(json) {
        $('&lt;h1/&gt;').text(json.title).appendTo('body');
        $('&lt;div class="content"/&gt;')
            .html(json.html).appendTo('body');
    },

    // code to run if the request fails;
    // the raw request and status codes are 
    // passed to the function
    error : function(xhr, status) {
        alert('Sorry, there was a problem!');
    },

    // code to run regardless of success or failure
    complete : function(xhr, status) {
        alert('The request is complete!');
    }
});</programlisting>
      </example>

      <note>
        <para>A note about the <code>dataType</code> setting: if the server
        sends back data that is in a different format than you specify, your
        code may fail, and the reason will not always be clear, because the
        HTTP response code will not show an error. When working with Ajax
        requests, make sure your server is sending back the data type you're
        asking for, and verify that the Content-type header is accurate for
        the data type. For example, for JSON data, the Content-type header
        should be <code>application/json</code>.</para>
      </note>

      <section>
        <title><code>$.ajax</code> Options</title>

        <para>There are many, many options for the $.ajax method, which is
        part of its power. For a complete list of options, visit <link
        xlink:href="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.ajax/">http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.ajax/</link>;
        here are several that you will use frequently:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>async</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set to <code>false</code> if the request should be sent
              synchronously. Defaults to <code>true</code>. Note that if you
              set this option to false, your request will block execution of
              other code until the response is received.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>cache</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Whether to use a cached response if available. Defaults to
              <code>true</code> for all dataTypes except "script" and "jsonp".
              When set to false, the URL will simply have a cachebusting
              parameter appended to it.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>complete</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A callback function to run when the request is complete,
              regardless of success or failure. The function receives the raw
              request object and the text status of the request.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>context</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The scope in which the callback function(s) should run
              (i.e. what <code>this</code> will mean inside the callback
              function(s)). By default, <code>this</code> inside the callback
              function(s) refers to the object originally passed to
              <code>$.ajax</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>data</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The data to be sent to the server. This can either be an
              object or a query string, such as
              <code>foo=bar&amp;baz=bim</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>dataType</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The type of data you expect back from the server. By
              default, jQuery will look at the MIME type of the response if no
              dataType is specified.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>error</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A callback function to run if the request results in an
              error. The function receives the raw request object and the text
              status of the request.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>jsonp</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The callback name to send in a query string when making a
              JSONP request. Defaults to "callback".</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>success</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A callback function to run if the request succeeds. The
              function receives the response data (converted to a JavaScript
              object if the dataType was JSON), as well as the text status of
              the request and the raw request object.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>timeout</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The time in milliseconds to wait before considering the
              request a failure.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>traditional</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set to true to use the param serialization style in use
              prior to jQuery 1.4. For details, see <link
              xlink:href="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.param/">http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.param/</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>type</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The type of the request, "POST" or "GET". Defaults to
              "GET". Other request types, such as "PUT" and "DELETE" can be
              used, but they may not be supported by all browsers.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>url</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The URL for the request.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>The <code>url</code> option is the only required property of the
        <code>$.ajax</code> configuration object; all other properties are
        optional.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Convenience Methods</title>

      <para>If you don't need the extensive configurability of
      <code>$.ajax</code>, and you don't care about handling errors, the Ajax
      convenience functions provided by jQuery can be useful, terse ways to
      accomplish Ajax requests. These methods are just "wrappers" around the
      core <code>$.ajax</code> method, and simply pre-set some of the options
      on the <code>$.ajax</code> method.</para>

      <para>The convenience methods provided by jQuery are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>$.get</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Perform a GET request to the provided URL.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>$.post</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Perform a POST request to the provided URL.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>$.getScript</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Add a script to the page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>$.getJSON</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Perform a GET request, and expect JSON to be
            returned.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>In each case, the methods take the following arguments, in
      order:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>url</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The URL for the request. Required.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>data</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The data to be sent to the server. Optional. This can either
            be an object or a query string, such as
            <code>foo=bar&amp;baz=bim</code>.</para>

            <note>
              <para>This option is not valid for
              <code>$.getScript</code>.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>success callback</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A callback function to run if the request succeeds.
            Optional. The function receives the response data (converted to a
            JavaScript object if the data type was JSON), as well as the text
            status of the request and the raw request object.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>data type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The type of data you expect back from the server.
            Optional.</para>

            <note>
              <para>This option is only applicable for methods that don't
              already specify the data type in their name.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <example>
        <title>Using jQuery's Ajax convenience methods</title>

        <para><programlisting>// get plain text or html
$.get('/users.php', { userId : 1234 }, function(resp) {
    console.log(resp);
});

// add a script to the page, then run a function defined in it
$.getScript('/static/js/myScript.js', function() {
    functionFromMyScript();
});

// get JSON-formatted data from the server
$.getJSON('/details.php', function(resp) {
    $.each(resp, function(k, v) {
        console.log(k + ' : ' + v);
    });
});</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><code>$.fn.load</code></title>

      <para>The <code>$.fn.load</code> method is unique among jQuery’s Ajax
      methods in that it is called on a selection. The <code>$.fn.load</code>
      method fetches HTML from a URL, and uses the returned HTML to populate
      the selected element(s). In addition to providing a URL to the method,
      you can optionally provide a selector; jQuery will fetch only the
      matching content from the returned HTML.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using <code>$.fn.load</code> to populate an element</title>

        <programlisting>$('#newContent').load('/foo.html');</programlisting>
      </example>

      <example>
        <title>Using <code>$.fn.load</code> to populate an element based on a
        selector</title>

        <programlisting>$('#newContent').load('/foo.html <emphasis role="bold">#myDiv h1:first</emphasis>', function(html) {
  alert('Content updated!');
});</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ajax and Forms</title>

    <para>jQuery’s ajax capabilities can be especially useful when dealing
    with forms. The <link xlink:href="http://jquery.malsup.com/form/">jQuery
    Form Plugin</link> is a well-tested tool for adding Ajax capabilities to
    forms, and you should generally use it for handling forms with Ajax rather
    than trying to roll your own solution for anything remotely complex. That
    said, there are a two jQuery methods you should know that relate to form
    processing in jQuery: <code>$.fn.serialize</code> and
    <code>$.fn.serializeArray</code>.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Turning form data into a query string</title>

      <programlisting>$('#myForm').serialize();</programlisting>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Creating an array of objects containing form data</title>

      <programlisting>$('#myForm').serializeArray();

// creates a structure like this:
[
    { name : 'field1', value : 123 },
    { name : 'field2', value : 'hello world' }
]</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working with JSONP</title>

    <para>The advent of JSONP -- essentially a consensual cross-site scripting
    hack -- has opened the door to powerful mashups of content. Many prominent
    sites provide JSONP services, allowing you access to their content via a
    predefined API. A particularly great source of JSONP-formatted data is the
    <link xlink:href="http://developer.yahoo.com/yql/console/">Yahoo! Query
    Language</link>, which we'll use in the following example to fetch news
    about cats.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Using YQL and JSONP</title>

      <programlisting>$.ajax({
    url : 'http://query.yahooapis.com/v1/public/yql',

    // the name of the callback parameter,
    // as specified by the YQL service
    jsonp : 'callback',

    // tell jQuery we're expecting JSONP
    dataType : 'jsonp',

    // tell YQL what we want and that we want JSON
    data : {
        q : 'select title,abstract,url from search.news where query="cat"',
        format : 'json'
    },

    // work with the response
    success : function(response) {
        console.log(response);
    }
});</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>jQuery handles all the complex aspects of JSONP behind-the-scenes --
    all we have to do is tell jQuery the name of the JSONP callback parameter
    specified by YQL ("callback" in this case), and otherwise the whole
    process looks and feels like a normal Ajax request.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ajax Events</title>

    <para>Often, you’ll want to perform an operation whenever an Ajax requests
    starts or stops, such as showing or hiding a loading indicator. Rather
    than defining this behavior inside every Ajax request, you can bind Ajax
    events to elements just like you'd bind other events. For a complete list
    of Ajax events, visit <link
    xlink:href="http://docs.jquery.com/Ajax_Events">http://docs.jquery.com/Ajax_Events</link>.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Setting up a loading indicator using Ajax Events</title>

      <programlisting>$('#loading_indicator')
    .ajaxStart(function() { $(this).show(); })
    .ajaxStop(function() { $(this).hide(); });</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <xi:include href="exercises/load-external-content.xml"
                xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="exercises/load-json.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />
  </section>
</chapter>
