<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Code Organization</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>When you move beyond adding simple enhancements to your website with
    jQuery and start developing full-blown client-side applications, you need
    to consider how to organize your code. In this chapter, we'll take a look
    at various code organization patterns you can use in your jQuery
    application and explore why code organization is important.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Key Concepts</title>

      <para>Before we jump into code organization patterns, it's important to
      understand some concepts that are common to all good code organization
      patterns.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Your code should be divided into units of functionality —
          modules, services, etc. Avoid the temptation to have all of your
          code in one huge <code>$(document).ready()</code> block. This
          concept, loosely, is known as encapsulation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Don't repeat yourself. Identify similarities among pieces of
          functionality, and use inheritance techniques to avoid repetitive
          code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Despite jQuery's DOM-centric nature, JavaScript applications
          are not all about the DOM. Remember that not all pieces of
          functionality need to — or should — have a DOM
          representation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Units of functionality should be <link
          xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loose_coupling">loosely
          coupled</link> — a unit of functionality should be able to exist on
          its own, and communication between units should be handled via a
          messaging system such as custom events or pub/sub. Stay away from
          direct communication between units of functionality whenever
          possible.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The concept of loose coupling can be especially troublesome to
      developers making their first foray into complex applications, so be
      mindful of this as you're getting started.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Encapsulation</title>

    <para>The first step to code organization is separating pieces of your
    application into distinct pieces; sometimes, even just this effort is
    sufficient to lend</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Object Literal</title>

      <para>An object literal is perhaps the simplest way to encapsulate
      related code. It doesn't offer any privacy for properties or methods,
      but it's useful for eliminating anonymous functions from your code,
      centralizing configuration options, and easing the path to reuse and
      refactoring.</para>

      <example>
        <title>An object literal</title>

        <programlisting>var myFeature = {
    myProperty : 'hello',

    myMethod : function() {
        console.log(myFeature.myProperty);
    },

    init : function(settings) {
        myFeature.settings = settings;
    },

    readSettings : function() {
        console.log(myFeature.settings);
    }
};

myFeature.myProperty; // 'hello'
myFeature.myMethod(); // logs 'hello'
myFeature.init({ foo : 'bar' });
myFeature.readSettings(); // logs { foo : 'bar' }
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The object literal above is simply an object assigned to a
      variable. The object has one property and several methods. All of the
      properties and methods are public, so any part of your application can
      see the properties and call methods on the object. While there is an
      init method, there's nothing requiring that it be called before the
      object is functional.</para>

      <para>How would we apply this pattern to jQuery code? Let's say that we
      had this code written in the traditional jQuery style:</para>

      <programlisting>// clicking on a list item loads some content
// using the list item's ID and hides content
// in sibling list items
$(document).ready(function() {
  $('#myFeature li')
    .append('&lt;div/&gt;')
    .click(function() {
      var $this = $(this);
      var $div = $this.find('div');
      $div.load('foo.php?item=' +
        $this.attr('id'), 
        function() {
          $div.show();
          $this.siblings()
            .find('div').hide();
        }
      );
    });
});
</programlisting>

      <para>If this were the extent of our application, leaving it as-is would
      be fine. On the other hand, if this was a piece of a larger application,
      we'd do well to keep this functionality separate from unrelated
      functionality. We might also want to move the URL out of the code and
      into a configuration area. Finally, we might want to break up the chain
      to make it easier to modify pieces of the functionality later.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using an object literal for a jQuery feature</title>

        <programlisting>var myFeature = {
    init : function(settings) {
        myFeature.config = {
            $items : $('#myFeature li'),
            $container : $('&lt;div class="container"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;'),
            urlBase : '/foo.php?item='
        };

        // allow overriding the default config
        $.extend(myFeature.config, settings);

        myFeature.setup();        
    },

    setup : function() {
        myFeature.config.$items
            .each(myFeature.createContainer)
            .click(myFeature.showItem);
    },

    createContainer : function() {
        var $i = $(this),
            $c = myFeature.config.$container.clone()
                     .appendTo($i);

        $i.data('container', $c);
    },
    
    buildUrl : function() {
        return myFeature.config.urlBase + 
               myFeature.$currentItem.attr('id');
    },
    
    showItem : function() {
        var myFeature.$currentItem = $(this);
        myFeature.getContent(myFeature.showContent);
    },
    
    getContent : function(callback) {
        var url = myFeature.buildUrl();
        myFeature.$currentItem
            .data('container').load(url, callback);
    },
    
    showContent : function() {
        myFeature.$currentItem
            .data('container').show();
        myFeature.hideContent();
    },
    
    hideContent : function() {
        myFeature.$currentItem.siblings()
            .each(function() { 
                $(this).data('container').hide(); 
            });
    }
};

$(document).ready(myFeature.init);</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The first thing you'll notice is that this approach is obviously
      far longer than the original — again, if this were the extent of our
      application, using an object literal would likely be overkill. Assuming
      it's not the extent of our application, though, we've gained several
      things:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>We've broken our feature up into tiny methods. In the future,
          if we want to change how content is shown, it's clear where to
          change it. In the original code, this step is much harder to
          locate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>We've eliminated the use of anonymous functions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>We've moved configuration options out of the body of the code
          and put them in a central location.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>We've eliminated the constraints of the chain, making the code
          easier to refactor, remix, and rearrange.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For non-trivial features, object literals are a clear improvement
      over a long stretch of code stuffed in a $(document).ready() block, as
      they get us thinking about the pieces of our functionality. However,
      they aren't a whole lot more advanced than simply having a bunch of
      function declarations inside of that $(document).ready() block.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Module Pattern</title>

      <para>The module pattern overcomes some of the limitations of the object
      literal, offering privacy for variables and functions while exposing a
      public API if desired.</para>

      <example>
        <title>The module pattern</title>

        <programlisting>var feature =(function() {

    // private variables and functions
    var privateThing = 'secret',
        publicThing = 'not secret',

        changePrivateThing = function() {
            privateThing = 'super secret';
        },

        sayPrivateThing = function() {
            console.log(privateThing);
            changePrivateThing();
        };

    // public API
    return {
        publicThing : publicThing,
        sayPrivateThing : sayPrivateThing
    }

})();

feature.publicThing; // 'not secret'

feature.sayPrivateThing(); 
// logs 'secret' and changes the value
// of privateThing</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>In the example above, we self-execute an anonymous function that
      returns an object. Inside of the function, we define some variables.
      Because the variables are defined inside of the function, we don't have
      access to them outside of the function unless we put them in the return
      object. This means that no code outside of the function has access to
      the <code>privateThing</code> variable or to the
      <code>changePrivateThing</code> function. However,
      <code>sayPrivateThing</code> does have access to
      <code>privateThing</code> and <code>changePrivateThing</code>, because
      both were defined in the same scope as
      <code>sayPrivateThing</code>.</para>

      <para>This pattern is powerful because, as you can gather from the
      variable names, it can give you private variables and functions while
      exposing a limited API consisting of the returned object's properties
      and methods.</para>

      <para>Below is a revised version of the previous example, showing how we
      could create the same feature using the module pattern while only
      exposing one public method of the module,
      <code>showItemByIndex()</code>.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using the module pattern for a jQuery feature</title>

        <programlisting>$(document).ready(function() {
    var feature = (function() {
        
        var $items = $('#myFeature li'),
            $container = $('&lt;div class="container"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;'),
            $currentItem,

            urlBase = '/foo.php?item=',
            
            createContainer = function() {
                var $i = $(this),
                    $c = $container.clone().appendTo($i);

                $i.data('container', $c);
            },
            
            buildUrl = function() {
                return urlBase + $currentItem.attr('id');
            },
            
            showItem = function() {
                var $currentItem = $(this);
                getContent(showContent);
            },
            
            showItemByIndex = function(idx) {
                $.proxy(showItem, $items.get(idx));
            },
            
            getContent = function(callback) {
                $currentItem.data('container').load(buildUrl(), callback);
            },
            
            showContent = function() {
                $currentItem.data('container').show();
                hideContent();
            },
            
            hideContent = function() {
                $currentItem.siblings()
                    .each(function() { 
                        $(this).data('container').hide(); 
                });
            };

        $items
            .each(createContainer)
            .click(showItem);
            
        return { showItemByIndex : showItemByIndex };
    })();
    
    feature.showItemByIndex(0);
});</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Inheritance</title>

    <para>Object literals and the module pattern, on their own, create only a
    single instance of the enclosed functionality. Sometimes essentially the
    same functionality exists several times throughout your code — for
    example, maybe there are a list of people on your page, and there is a set
    of behavior associated with each person. In these cases, you need a way to
    create multiple instances of a feature and to share code across similar
    features.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Prototypal Inheritance</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Classical Inheritance</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>It's Not All About the DOM</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Communication Between Components</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Managing Dependencies</title>

    <note>
      <para>This section is based heavily on the excellent RequireJS
      documentation at <link
      xlink:href="http://requirejs.org/docs/jquery.html">http://requirejs.org/docs/jquery.html</link>,
      and is used with the permission of RequireJS author James Burke.</para>
    </note>

    <para>When a project reaches a certain size, managing the script modules
    for a project starts to get tricky. You need to be sure to sequence the
    scripts in the right order, and you need to start seriously thinking about
    combining scripts together into a bundle for deployment, so that only one
    or a very small number of requests are made to load the scripts. You may
    also want to load code on the fly, after page load. </para>

    <para>RequireJS, a dependency management tool by James Burke, can help you
    manage the script modules, load them in the right order, and make it easy
    to combine the scripts later via the RequireJS optimization tool without
    needing to change your markup. It also gives you an easy way to load
    scripts after the page has loaded, allowing you to spread out the download
    size over time. </para>

    <para>RequireJS has a module system that lets you define well-scoped
    modules, but you do not have to follow that system to get the benefits of
    dependency management and build-time optimizations. Over time, if you
    start to create more modular code that needs to be reused in a few places,
    the module format for RequireJS makes it easy to write encapsulated code
    that can be loaded on the fly. It can grow with you, particularly if you
    want to incorporate internationalization (i18n) string bundles, to
    localize your project for different languages, or load some HTML strings
    and make sure those strings are available before executing code, or even
    use JSONP services as dependencies.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting RequireJS</title>

      <para>The easiest way to use RequireJS with jQuery is to <link
      xlink:href="http://requirejs.org/docs/download.html">download a build of
      jQuery that has RequireJS built in</link>. This build excludes portions
      of RequireJS that duplicate jQuery functionality. You may also find it
      useful to download <link
      xlink:href="http://requirejs.org/docs/release/0.11.0/jquery-require-sample.zip">a
      sample jQuery project that uses RequireJS</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using RequireJS with jQuery</title>

      <para>Using RequireJS in your page is simple: just include the jQuery
      that has RequireJS built in, then require your application files. The
      following example assumes that the jQuery build, and your other scripts,
      are all in a <filename>scripts/</filename> directory.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using RequireJS: A simple example</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;jQuery+RequireJS Sample Page&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;script src="scripts/require-jquery.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
        &lt;script&gt;require(["app"]);&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;h1&gt;jQuery+RequireJS Sample Page&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The call to <code>require(["app"])</code> tells RequireJS to load
      the <filename>scripts/app.js</filename> file. RequireJS will load any
      dependency that is passed to <code>require()</code> without a
      <filename>.js</filename> extension from the same directory as
      <filename>require-jquery.js</filename>, though this can be configured to
      behave differently. If you feel more comfortable specifying the whole
      path, you can also do the following: </para>

      <programlisting>&lt;script&gt;require(["scripts/app.js"]);&lt;/script&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>What is in <filename>app.js</filename>? Another call to
      <filename>require.js</filename> to load all the scripts you need and any
      init work you want to do for the page. This example
      <filename>app.js</filename> script loads two plugins,
      <filename>jquery.alpha.js</filename> and
      <filename>jquery.beta.js</filename> (not the names of real plugins, just
      an example). The plugins should be in the same directory as
      <filename>require-jquery.js</filename>: </para>

      <example>
        <title>A simple JavaScript file with dependencies</title>

        <programlisting>require(["jquery.alpha", "jquery.beta"], function() {
    //the jquery.alpha.js and jquery.beta.js plugins have been loaded.
    $(function() {
        $('body').alpha().beta();
    });
});</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating Reusable Modules with RequireJS</title>

      <para>RequireJS makes it easy to define reusable modules via
      <code>require.def()</code>. A RequireJS module can have dependencies
      that can be used to define a module, and a RequireJS module can return a
      value — an object, a function, whatever — that can then be consumed by
      yet other modules.</para>

      <para>If your module does not have any dependencies, then just specify
      the name of the module as the first argument to
      <code>require.def()</code>. The second argument is just an object
      literal that defines the module's properties. For example: </para>

      <example>
        <title>Defining a RequireJS module that has no dependencies</title>

        <programlisting>require.def("my/simpleshirt",
    {
        color: "black",
        size: "unisize"
    }
);</programlisting>

        <para>This example would be stored in a my/simpleshirt.js file.
        </para>

        <para>If your module has dependencies, you can specify the
        dependencies as the second argument to <code>require.def()</code> (as
        an array) and then pass a function as the third argument. The function
        will be called to define the module once all dependencies have loaded.
        The function receives the values returned by the dependencies as its
        arguments (in the same order they were required in the array), and the
        function should return an object that defines the module.</para>

        <example>
          <title>Defining a RequireJS module with dependencies</title>

          <programlisting>require.def("my/shirt",
    ["my/cart", "my/inventory"],
    function(cart, inventory) {
        //return an object to define the "my/shirt" module.
        return {
            color: "blue",
            size: "large"
            addToCart: function() {
                inventory.decrement(this);
                cart.add(this);
            }
        }
    }
);</programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>In this example, a my/shirt module is created. It depends on
        my/cart and my/inventory. On disk, the files are structured like this:
        </para>

        <programlisting>my/cart.js
my/inventory.js
my/shirt.js</programlisting>

        <para>The function that defines <code>my/shirt</code> is not called
        until the <code>my/cart</code> and <code>my/inventory</code> modules
        have been loaded, and the function receives the modules as the
        <code>cart</code> and <code>inventory</code> arguments. The order of
        the function arguments must match the order in which the dependencies
        were required in the dependencies array. The object returned by the
        function call defines the <code>my/shirt</code> module. Be defining
        modules in this way, <code>my/shirt</code> does not exist as a global
        object. Modules that define globals are explicitly discouraged, so
        multiple versions of a module can exist in a page at a time. </para>

        <para>Modules do not have to return objects; any valid return value
        from a function is allowed.</para>

        <example>
          <title>Defining a RequireJS module that returns a function</title>

          <programlisting>require.def("my/title",
    ["my/dependency1", "my/dependency2"],
    function(dep1, dep2) {
        //return a function to define "my/title". It gets or sets
        //the window title.
        return function(title) {
            return title ? (window.title = title) : window.title;
        }
    }
);</programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>Only one module should be required per JavaScript file.</para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Optimizing Your Code: The RequireJS Build Tool</title>

      <para>Once you incorporate RequireJS for dependency management, your
      page is set up to be optimized very easily. Download the RequireJS
      source and place it anywhere you like, preferrably somewhere outside
      your web development area. For the purposes of this example, the
      RequireJS source is placed as a sibling to the
      <filename>webapp</filename> directory, which contains the HTML page and
      the scripts directory with all the scripts. Complete directory
      structure: </para>

      <programlisting>requirejs/ (used for the build tools)
webapp/app.html
webapp/scripts/app.js
webapp/scripts/require-jquery.js
webapp/scripts/jquery.alpha.js
webapp/scripts/jquery.beta.js</programlisting>

      <para>Then, in the scripts directory that has
      <filename>require-jquery.js</filename> and app.js, create a file called
      app.build.js with the following contents: </para>

      <example>
        <title>A RequireJS build configuration file</title>

        <programlisting>{
    appDir: "../",
    baseUrl: "scripts/",
    dir: "../../webapp-build",
    //Comment out the optimize line if you want
    //the code minified by Closure Compiler using
    //the "simple" optimizations mode
    optimize: "none",

    modules: [
        {
            name: "app"
        }
    ]
}</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>To use the build tool, you need Java 6 installed. Closure Compiler
      is used for the JavaScript minification step (if <code>optimize:
      "none"</code> is commented out), and it requires Java 6. </para>

      <para>To start the build, go to the webapp/scripts directory, execute
      the following command: </para>

      <programlisting># non-windows systems
../../requirejs/build/build.sh app.build.js

# windows systems
..\..\requirejs\build\build.bat app.build.js</programlisting>

      <para>Now, in the webapp-build directory, <filename>app.js</filename>
      will have the <filename>app.js</filename> contents,
      <filename>jquery.alpha.js</filename> and
      <filename>jquery.beta.js</filename> inlined. If you then load the
      <filename>app.html</filename> file in the
      <filename>webapp-build</filename> directory, you should not see any
      network requests for <filename>jquery.alpha.js</filename> and
      <filename>jquery.beta.js</filename>. </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <section>
      <title>Create a Portlet Module</title>

      <para>Open the file <filename>/exercises/portlets.html</filename> in
      your browser. Use the file
      <filename>/exercises/js/portlets.js</filename>. Your task is to create a
      portlet creation function that uses the module pattern, such that the
      following code will work:</para>

      <programlisting>var myPortlet = Portlet({
    title : 'Curry',
    source : 'data/html/curry.html',
    initialState : 'open' // or 'closed'
});

myPortlet.$element.appendTo('body');</programlisting>

      <para>Each portlet should be a div with a title, a content area, a
      button to open/close the portlet, a button to remove the portlet, and a
      button to refresh the portlet. The portlet returned by the Portlet
      function should have the following public API:</para>

      <programlisting>myPortlet.open(); // force open state
myPortlet.close(); // force close state
myPortlet.toggle(); // toggle open/close state
myPortlet.refresh(); // refresh the content
myPortlet.destroy(); // remove the portlet from the page
myPortlet.setSource('data/html/onions.html'); 
// change the source</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
