<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Plugins</title>

  <section>
    <title>What exactly is a plugin?</title>

    <para>A jQuery plugin is simply a new method that we use to extend
    jQuery's prototype object. By extending the prototype object you enable
    all jQuery objects to inherit any methods that you add. As established,
    whenever you call <code>jQuery()</code> you're creating a new jQuery
    object, with all of jQuery's methods inherited.</para>

    <para>The idea of a plugin is to do something with a collection of
    elements. You could consider each method that comes with the jQuery core a
    plugin, like <code>fadeOut</code> or <code>addClass</code>.</para>

    <para>You can make your own plugins and use them privately in your code or
    you can release them into the wild. There are thousands of jQuery plugins
    available online. The barrier to creating a plugin of your own is so low
    that you'll want to do it straight away!</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to create a basic plugin</title>

    <para>The notation for creating a typical plugin is as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>(function($){
    $.fn.myNewPlugin = function() {
        return this.each(function(){
            // do something
        });
    };
}(jQuery));</programlisting>

    <para>Don't let that confuse you though. The point of a jQuery plugin is
    to extend jQuery's prototype object, and that's what's happening on this
    line:</para>

    <programlisting>$.fn.myNewPlugin = function() { //...</programlisting>

    <para>We wrap this assignment in an immediately-invoked function:</para>

    <programlisting>(function($){
    //...
}(jQuery));</programlisting>

    <para>This has the effect of creating a "private" scope that allows us to
    extend jQuery using the dollar symbol without having to risk the
    possibility that the dollar has been over-written by another
    library.</para>

    <para>So our actual plugin, thus far, is this:</para>

    <programlisting>$.fn.myNewPlugin = function() {
    return this.each(function(){
        // do something
    });
};</programlisting>

    <para>The <code>this</code> keyword within the new plugin refers to the
    jQuery object on which the plugin is being called.</para>

    <programlisting>var somejQueryObject = $('#something');

$.fn.myNewPlugin = function() {
    alert(this === somejQueryObject);
};

somejQueryObject.myNewPlugin(); // alerts 'true'</programlisting>

    <para>Your typical jQuery object will contain references to any number of
    DOM elements, and that's why jQuery objects are often referred to as
    collections.</para>

    <para>So, to do something with a collection we need to loop through it,
    which is most easily achieved using jQuery's <code>each()</code>
    method:</para>

    <programlisting>$.fn.myNewPlugin = function() {
    return this.each(function(){
    
    });
};</programlisting>

    <para>jQuery's <code>each()</code> method, like most other jQuery methods,
    returns a jQuery object, thus enabling what we've all come to know and
    love as 'chaining' (<code>$(...).css().attr()...</code>). We wouldn't want
    to break this convention so we return the <code>this</code> object. Within
    this loop you can do whatever you want with each element. Here's an
    example of a small plugin using some of the techniques we've
    discussed:</para>

    <programlisting>(function($){
    $.fn.showLinkLocation = function() {
        return this.filter('a').each(function(){
            $(this).append(
                ' (' + $(this).attr('href') + ')'
            );
        });
    };
}(jQuery));
    
// Usage example:
$('a').showLinkLocation();</programlisting>

    <para>This handy plugin goes through all anchors in the collection and
    appends the <code>href</code> attribute in brackets.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;!-- Before plugin is called: --&gt;
&lt;a href="page.html"&gt;Foo&lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;!-- After plugin is called: --&gt;
&lt;a href="page.html"&gt;Foo (page.html)&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Our plugin can be optimised though:</para>

    <programlisting>(function($){
    $.fn.showLinkLocation = function() {
        return this.filter('a').append(function(){
              return ' (' + this.href + ')';
        });
    };
}(jQuery));</programlisting>

    <para>We're using the <code>append</code> method's capability to accept a
    callback, and the return value of that callback will determine what is
    appended to each element in the collection. Notice also that we're not
    using the <code>attr</code> method to retrieve the <code>href</code>
    attribute, because the native DOM API gives us easy access with the aptly
    named <code>href</code> property.</para>

    <para>Here's another example of a plugin. This one doesn't require us to
    loop through every elememt with the <code>each()</code> method. Instead,
    we're simply going to delegate to other jQuery methods directly:</para>

    <programlisting>(function($){
    $.fn.fadeInAndAddClass = function(duration, className) {
        return this.fadeIn(duration, function(){
            $(this).addClass(className);
        });
    };
}(jQuery));
    
// Usage example:
$('a').fadeInAndAddClass(400, 'finishedFading');</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Finding &amp; Evaluating Plugins</title>

    <para>Plugins extend the basic jQuery functionality, and one of the most
    celebrated aspects of the library is its extensive plugin ecosystem. From
    table sorting to form validation to autocompletion ... if there’s a need
    for it, chances are good that someone has written a plugin for it.</para>

    <para>The quality of jQuery plugins varies widely. Many plugins are
    extensively tested and well-maintained, but others are hastily created and
    then ignored. More than a few fail to follow best practices.</para>

    <para>Google is your best initial resource for locating plugins, though
    the jQuery team is working on an improved plugin repository. Once you’ve
    identified some options via a Google search, you may want to consult the
    jQuery mailing list or the #jquery IRC channel to get input from
    others.</para>

    <para>When looking for a plugin to fill a need, do your homework. Ensure
    that the plugin is well-documented, and look for the author to provide
    lots of examples of its use. Be wary of plugins that do far more than you
    need; they can end up adding substantial overhead to your page. For more
    tips on spotting a subpar plugin, read <link
    xlink:href="http://remysharp.com/2010/06/03/signs-of-a-poorly-written-jquery-plugin/">Signs
    of a poorly written jQuery plugin</link> by Remy Sharp.</para>

    <para>Once you choose a plugin, you’ll need to add it to your page.
    Download the plugin, unzip it if necessary, place it your application’s
    directory structure, then include the plugin in your page using a script
    tag (after you include jQuery).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Writing Plugins</title>

    <para>Sometimes you want to make a piece of functionality available
    throughout your code; for example, perhaps you want a single method you
    can call on a jQuery selection that performs a series of operations on the
    selection. In this case, you may want to write a plugin.</para>

    <para>Most plugins are simply methods created in the <code>$.fn</code>
    namespace. jQuery guarantees that a method called on a jQuery object will
    be able to access that jQuery object as <code>this</code> inside the
    method. In return, your plugin needs to guarantee that it returns the same
    object it received, unless explicitly documented otherwise.</para>

    <para>Here is an example of a simple plugin:</para>

    <example>
      <title>Creating a plugin to add and remove a class on hover</title>

      <programlisting>// defining the plugin
(function($){
    $.fn.hoverClass = function(c) {
        return this.hover(
            function() { $(this).toggleClass(c); }
        );
    };
}(jQuery);

// using the plugin
$('li').hoverClass('hover');</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>For more on plugin development, read Mike Alsup's essential post,
    <link
    xlink:href="http://www.learningjquery.com/2007/10/a-plugin-development-pattern">A
    Plugin Development Pattern</link>. In it, he creates a plugin called
    <code>$.fn.hilight</code>, which provides support for the metadata plugin
    if it's present, and provides a centralized method for setting global and
    instance options for the plugin.</para>

    <example>
      <title>The Mike Alsup jQuery Plugin Development Pattern</title>

      <programlisting>//
// create closure
//
(function($) {
  //
  // plugin definition
  //
  $.fn.hilight = function(options) {
    debug(this);
    // build main options before element iteration
    var opts = $.extend({}, $.fn.hilight.defaults, options);
    // iterate and reformat each matched element
    return this.each(function() {
      $this = $(this);
      // build element specific options
      var o = $.meta ? $.extend({}, opts, $this.data()) : opts;
      // update element styles
      $this.css({
        backgroundColor: o.background,
        color: o.foreground
      });
      var markup = $this.html();
      // call our format function
      markup = $.fn.hilight.format(markup);
      $this.html(markup);
    });
  };
  //
  // private function for debugging
  //
  function debug($obj) {
    if (window.console &amp;&amp; window.console.log)
      window.console.log('hilight selection count: ' + $obj.size());
  };
  //
  // define and expose our format function
  //
  $.fn.hilight.format = function(txt) {
    return '&lt;strong&gt;' + txt + '&lt;/strong&gt;';
  };
  //
  // plugin defaults
  //
  $.fn.hilight.defaults = {
    foreground: 'red',
    background: 'yellow'
  };
//
// end of closure
//
})(jQuery);</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Writing Stateful Plugins with the jQuery UI Widget Factory</title>

    <para>
      <note>
        <para>This section is based, with permission, on the blog post <link
        xlink:href="http://blog.nemikor.com/2010/05/15/building-stateful-jquery-plugins/">Building
        Stateful jQuery Plugins</link> by Scott Gonzalez.</para>
      </note>While most existing jQuery plugins are stateless — that is, we
    call them on an element and that is the extent of our interaction with the
    plugin — there’s a large set of functionality that doesn’t fit into the
    basic plugin pattern.</para>

    <para>In order to fill this gap, jQuery UI has implemented a more advanced
    plugin system. The new system manages state, allows multiple functions to
    be exposed via a single plugin, and provides various extension points.
    This system is called the widget factory and is exposed as
    <code>jQuery.widget</code> as part of jQuery UI 1.8; however, it can be
    used independently of jQuery UI. </para>

    <para>To demonstrate the capabilities of the widget factory, we'll build a
    simple progress bar plugin. </para>

    <para>To start, we’ll create a progress bar that just lets us set the
    progress once. As we can see below, this is done by calling
    <code>jQuery.widget</code> with two parameters: the name of the plugin to
    create and an object literal containing functions to support our plugin.
    When our plugin gets called, it will create a new plugin instance and all
    functions will be executed within the context of that instance. This is
    different from a standard jQuery plugin in two important ways. First, the
    context is an object, not a DOM element. Second, the context is always a
    single object, never a collection. </para>

    <example>
      <title>A simple, stateful plugin using the jQuery UI widget
      factory</title>

      <programlisting>$.widget("nmk.progressbar", {
    _create: function() {
        var progress = this.options.value + "%";
        this.element
            .addClass("progressbar")
            .text(progress);
    }
});</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>The name of the plugin must contain a namespace; in this case we’ve
    used the <code>nmk</code> namespace. There is a limitation that namespaces
    be exactly one level deep — that is, we can't use a namespace like
    <code>nmk.foo</code>. We can also see that the widget factory has provided
    two properties for us. <code>this.element</code> is a jQuery object
    containing exactly one element. If our plugin is called on a jQuery object
    containing multiple elements, a separate plugin instance will be created
    for each element, and each instance will have its own
    <code>this.element</code>. The second property, <code>this.options</code>,
    is a hash containing key/value pairs for all of our plugin’s options.
    These options can be passed to our plugin as shown here. </para>

    <note>
      <para>In our example we use the <code>nmk</code> namespace. The
      <code>ui</code> namespace is reserved for official jQuery UI plugins.
      When building your own plugins, you should create your own namespace.
      This makes it clear where the plugin came from and whether it is part of
      a larger collection.</para>
    </note>

    <example>
      <title>Passing options to a widget</title>

      <programlisting>$("&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;")
    .appendTo( "body" )
    .progressbar({ value: 20 });</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>When we call <code>jQuery.widget</code> it extends jQuery by adding
    a method to <code>jQuery.fn</code> (the same way we'd create a standard
    plugin). The name of the function it adds is based on the name you pass to
    <code>jQuery.widget</code>, without the namespace; in our case it will
    create <code>jQuery.fn.progressbar</code>. The options passed to our
    plugin get set in <code>this.options</code> inside of our plugin instance.
    As shown below, we can specify default values for any of our options. When
    designing your API, you should figure out the most common use case for
    your plugin so that you can set appropriate default values and make all
    options truly optional. </para>

    <example>
      <title>Setting default options for a widget</title>

      <programlisting>$.widget("nmk.progressbar", {
    // default options
    options: {
        value: 0
    },

    _create: function() {
        var progress = this.options.value + "%";
        this.element
            .addClass( "progressbar" )
            .text( progress );
    }
});</programlisting>
    </example>

    <section>
      <title>Adding Methods to a Widget</title>

      <para>Now that we can initialize our progress bar, we’ll add the ability
      to perform actions by calling methods on our plugin instance. To define
      a plugin method, we just include the function in the object literal that
      we pass to <code>jQuery.widget</code>. We can also define “private”
      methods by prepending an underscore to the function name. </para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating widget methods</title>

        <programlisting>$.widget("nmk.progressbar", {
    options: {
        value: 0
    },

    _create: function() {
        var progress = this.options.value + "%";
        this.element
            .addClass("progressbar")
            .text(progress);
    },

    // create a public method
    value: function(value) {
        // no value passed, act as a getter
        if (value === undefined) {
            return this.options.value;
        // value passed, act as a setter
        } else {
            this.options.value = this._constrain(value);
            var progress = this.options.value + "%";
            this.element.text(progress);
        }
    },

    // create a private method
    _constrain: function(value) {
        if (value &gt; 100) {
            value = 100;
        }
        if (value &lt; 0) {
            value = 0;
        }
        return value;
    }
});
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>To call a method on a plugin instance, you pass the name of the
      method to the jQuery plugin. If you are calling a method that accepts
      parameters, you simply pass those parameters after the method name.
      </para>

      <example>
        <title>Calling methods on a plugin instance</title>

        <programlisting>var bar = $("&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;")
    .appendTo("body")
    .progressbar({ value: 20 });

// get the current value
alert(bar.progressbar("value"));

// update the value
bar.progressbar("value", 50);

// get the current value again
alert(bar.progressbar("value"));</programlisting>
      </example>

      <note>
        <para>Executing methods by passing the method name to the same jQuery
        function that was used to initialize the plugin may seem odd. This is
        done to prevent pollution of the jQuery namespace while maintaining
        the ability to chain method calls. </para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Working with Widget Options</title>

      <para>One of the methods that is automatically available to our plugin
      is the <code>option</code> method. The option method allows you to get
      and set options after initialization. This method works exactly like
      jQuery’s css and attr methods: you can pass just a name to use it as a
      setter, a name and value to use it as a single setter, or a hash of
      name/value pairs to set multiple values. When used as a getter, the
      plugin will return the current value of the option that corresponds to
      the name that was passed in. When used as a setter, the plugin’s
      <code>_setOption</code> method will be called for each option that is
      being set. We can specify a <code>_setOption</code> method in our plugin
      to react to option changes. </para>

      <example>
        <title>Responding when an option is set</title>

        <programlisting>$.widget("nmk.progressbar", {
    options: {
        value: 0
    },

    _create: function() {
        this.element.addClass("progressbar");
        this._update();
    },

    _setOption: function(key, value) {
        this.options[key] = value;
        this._update();
    },

    _update: function() {
        var progress = this.options.value + "%";
        this.element.text(progress);
    }
});</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding Callbacks</title>

      <para>One of the easiest ways to make your plugin extensible is to add
      callbacks so users can react when the state of your plugin changes. We
      can see below how to add a callback to our progress bar to signify when
      the progress has reached 100%. The <code>_trigger</code> method takes
      three parameters: the name of the callback, a native event object that
      initiated the callback, and a hash of data relevant to the event. The
      callback name is the only required parameter, but the others can be very
      useful for users who want to implement custom functionality on top of
      your plugin. For example, if we were building a draggable plugin, we
      could pass the native mousemove event when triggering a drag callback;
      this would allow users to react to the drag based on the x/y coordinates
      provided by the event object. </para>

      <example>
        <title>Providing callbacks for user extension</title>

        <programlisting>$.widget("nmk.progressbar", {
    options: {
        value: 0
    },

    _create: function() {
        this.element.addClass("progressbar");
        this._update();
    },

    _setOption: function(key, value) {
        this.options[key] = value;
        this._update();
    },

    _update: function() {
        var progress = this.options.value + "%";
        this.element.text(progress);
        if (this.options.value == 100) {
            this._trigger("complete", null, { value: 100 });
        }
    }
});</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Callback functions are essentially just additional options, so you
      can get and set them just like any other option. Whenever a callback is
      executed, a corresponding event is triggered as well. The event type is
      determined by concatenating the plugin name and the callback name. The
      callback and event both receive the same two parameters: an event object
      and a hash of data relevant to the event, as we’ll see below. </para>

      <para>If your plugin has functionality that you want to allow the user
      to prevent, the best way to support this is by creating cancelable
      callbacks. Users can cancel a callback, or its associated event, the
      same way they cancel any native event: by calling
      <code>event.preventDefault()</code> or using <code>return false</code>.
      If the user cancels the callback, the <code>_trigger</code> method will
      return false so you can implement the appropriate functionality within
      your plugin. </para>

      <example>
        <title>Binding to widget events</title>

        <programlisting>var bar = $("&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;")
    .appendTo("body")
    .progressbar({
        complete: function(event, data) {
            alert( "Callbacks are great!" );
        }
    })
    .bind("progressbarcomplete", function(event, data) {
        alert("Events bubble and support many handlers for extreme flexibility.");
        alert("The progress bar value is " + data.value);
    });

bar.progressbar("option", "value", 100);</programlisting>
      </example>

      <sidebar>
        <title>The Widget Factory: Under the Hood</title>

        <para>When you call <code>jQuery.widget</code>, it creates a
        constructor function for your plugin and sets the object literal that
        you pass in as the prototype for your plugin instances. All of the
        functionality that automatically gets added to your plugin comes from
        a base widget prototype, which is defined as
        <code>jQuery.Widget.prototype</code>. When a plugin instance is
        created, it is stored on the original DOM element using
        <code>jQuery.data</code>, with the plugin name as the key.</para>

        <para>Because the plugin instance is directly linked to the DOM
        element, you can access the plugin instance directly instead of going
        through the exposed plugin method if you want. This will allow you to
        call methods directly on the plugin instance instead of passing method
        names as strings and will also give you direct access to the plugin’s
        properties. </para>

        <programlisting>var bar = $("&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;")
    .appendTo("body")
    .progressbar()
    .data("progressbar" );

// call a method directly on the plugin instance
bar.option("value", 50);

// access properties on the plugin instance
alert(bar.options.value);</programlisting>

        <para>One of the biggest benefits of having a constructor and
        prototype for a plugin is the ease of extending the plugin. By adding
        or modifying methods on the plugin’s prototype, we can modify the
        behavior of all instances of our plugin. For example, if we wanted to
        add a method to our progress bar to reset the progress to 0% we could
        add this method to the prototype and it would instantly be available
        to be called on any plugin instance. </para>

        <programlisting>$.nmk.progressbar.prototype.reset = function() {
    this._setOption("value", 0);
};</programlisting>
      </sidebar>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cleaning Up</title>

      <para>In some cases, it will make sense to allow users to apply and then
      later unapply your plugin. You can accomplish this via the destroy
      method. Within the <code>destroy</code> method, you should undo anything
      your plugin may have done during initialization or later use. The
      <code>destroy</code> method is automatically called if the element that
      your plugin instance is tied to is removed from the DOM, so this can be
      used for garbage collection as well. The default <code>destroy</code>
      method removes the link between the DOM element and the plugin instance,
      so it’s important to call the base function from your plugin’s
      <code>destroy</code> method. </para>

      <example>
        <title>Adding a destroy method to a widget</title>

        <programlisting>$.widget( "nmk.progressbar", {
    options: {
        value: 0
    },

    _create: function() {
        this.element.addClass("progressbar");
        this._update();
    },

    _setOption: function(key, value) {
        this.options[key] = value;
        this._update();
    },

    _update: function() {
        var progress = this.options.value + "%";
        this.element.text(progress);
        if (this.options.value == 100 ) {
            this._trigger("complete", null, { value: 100 });
        }
    },

    destroy: function() {
        this.element
            .removeClass("progressbar")
            .text("");

        // call the base destroy function
        $.Widget.prototype.destroy.call(this);
    }
});</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Conclusion</title>

      <para>The widget factory is only one way of creating stateful plugins.
      There are a few different models that can be used and each have their
      own advantages and disadvantages. The widget factory solves lots of
      common problems for you and can greatly improve productivity, it also
      greatly improves code reuse, making it a great fit for jQuery UI as well
      as many other stateful plugins. </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <xi:include href="exercises/sortable-plugin.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="exercises/striping-plugin.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />
  </section>
</chapter>
