<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Code Organization</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>When you move beyond adding simple enhancements to your website with
    jQuery and start developing full-blown client-side applications, you need
    to consider how to organize your code. In this chapter, we'll take a look
    at various code organization patterns you can use in your jQuery
    application and explore why code organization is important.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Key Concepts</title>

      <para>Before we jump into code organization patterns, it's important to
      understand some concepts that are common to all good code organization
      patterns.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Your code should be divided into units of functionality —
          modules, services, etc. Avoid the temptation to have all of your
          code in one huge <code>$(document).ready()</code> block. This
          concept, loosely, is known as encapsulation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Don't repeat yourself. Identify similarities among pieces of
          functionality, and use inheritance techniques to avoid repetitive
          code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Despite jQuery's DOM-centric nature, JavaScript applications
          are not all about the DOM. Remember that not all pieces of
          functionality need to — or should — have a DOM
          representation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Units of functionality should be <link
          xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loose_coupling">loosely
          coupled</link> — a unit of functionality should be able to exist on
          its own, and communication between units should be handled via a
          messaging system such as custom events or pub/sub. Stay away from
          direct communication between units of functionality whenever
          possible.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The concept of loose coupling can be especially troublesome to
      developers making their first foray into complex applications, so be
      mindful of this as you're getting started.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Encapsulation</title>

    <para>The first step to code organization is separating pieces of your
    application into distinct pieces; sometimes, even just this effort is
    sufficient to lend</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Object Literal</title>

      <para>An object literal is perhaps the simplest way to encapsulate
      related code. It doesn't offer any privacy for properties or methods,
      but it's useful for eliminating anonymous functions from your code,
      centralizing configuration options, and easing the path to reuse and
      refactoring.</para>

      <example>
        <title>An object literal</title>

        <programlisting>var myFeature = {
    myProperty : 'hello',

    myMethod : function() {
        console.log(myFeature.myProperty);
    },

    init : function(settings) {
        myFeature.settings = settings;
    },

    readSettings : function() {
        console.log(myFeature.settings);
    }
};

myFeature.myProperty; // 'hello'
myFeature.myMethod(); // logs 'hello'
myFeature.init({ foo : 'bar' });
myFeature.readSettings(); // logs { foo : 'bar' }
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The object literal above is simply an object assigned to a
      variable. The object has one property and several methods. All of the
      properties and methods are public, so any part of your application can
      see the properties and call methods on the object. While there is an
      init method, there's nothing requiring that it be called before the
      object is functional.</para>

      <para>How would we apply this pattern to jQuery code? Let's say that we
      had this code written in the traditional jQuery style:</para>

      <programlisting>// clicking on a list item loads some content
// using the list item's ID and hides content
// in sibling list items
$(document).ready(function() {
  $('#myFeature li')
    .append('&lt;div/&gt;')
    .click(function() {
      var $this = $(this);
      var $div = $this.find('div');
      $div.load('foo.php?item=' +
        $this.attr('id'), 
        function() {
          $div.show();
          $this.siblings()
            .find('div').hide();
        }
      );
    });
});
</programlisting>

      <para>If this were the extent of our application, leaving it as-is would
      be fine. On the other hand, if this was a piece of a larger application,
      we'd do well to keep this functionality separate from unrelated
      functionality. We might also want to move the URL out of the code and
      into a configuration area. Finally, we might want to break up the chain
      to make it easier to modify pieces of the functionality later.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using an object literal for a jQuery feature</title>

        <programlisting>var myFeature = {
    init : function(settings) {
        myFeature.config = {
            $items : $('#myFeature li'),
            $container : $('&lt;div class="container"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;'),
            urlBase : '/foo.php?item='
        };

        // allow overriding the default config
        $.extend(myFeature.config, settings);

        myFeature.setup();        
    },

    setup : function() {
        myFeature.config.$items
            .each(myFeature.createContainer)
            .click(myFeature.showItem);
    },

    createContainer : function() {
        var $i = $(this),
            $c = myFeature.config.$container.clone()
                     .appendTo($i);

        $i.data('container', $c);
    },
    
    buildUrl : function() {
        return myFeature.config.urlBase + 
               myFeature.$currentItem.attr('id');
    },
    
    showItem : function() {
        var myFeature.$currentItem = $(this);
        myFeature.getContent(myFeature.showContent);
    },
    
    getContent : function(callback) {
        var url = myFeature.buildUrl();
        myFeature.$currentItem
            .data('container').load(url, callback);
    },
    
    showContent : function() {
        myFeature.$currentItem
            .data('container').show();
        myFeature.hideContent();
    },
    
    hideContent : function() {
        myFeature.$currentItem.siblings()
            .each(function() { 
                $(this).data('container').hide(); 
            });
    }
};

$(document).ready(myFeature.init);</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The first thing you'll notice is that this approach is obviously
      far longer than the original — again, if this were the extent of our
      application, using an object literal would likely be overkill. Assuming
      it's not the extent of our application, though, we've gained several
      things:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>We've broken our feature up into tiny methods. In the future,
          if we want to change how content is shown, it's clear where to
          change it. In the original code, this step is much harder to
          locate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>We've eliminated the use of anonymous functions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>We've moved configuration options out of the body of the code
          and put them in a central location.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>We've eliminated the constraints of the chain, making the code
          easier to refactor, remix, and rearrange.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For non-trivial features, object literals are a clear improvement
      over a long stretch of code stuffed in a $(document).ready() block, as
      they get us thinking about the pieces of our functionality. However,
      they aren't a whole lot more advanced than simply having a bunch of
      function declarations inside of that $(document).ready() block.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Module Pattern</title>

      <para>The module pattern overcomes some of the limitations of the object
      literal, offering privacy for variables and functions while exposing a
      public API if desired.</para>

      <example>
        <title>The module pattern</title>

        <programlisting>var feature =(function() {

    // private variables and functions
    var privateThing = 'secret',
        publicThing = 'not secret',

        changePrivateThing = function() {
            privateThing = 'super secret';
        },

        sayPrivateThing = function() {
            console.log(privateThing);
            changePrivateThing();
        };

    // public API
    return {
        publicThing : publicThing,
        sayPrivateThing : sayPrivateThing
    }

})();

feature.publicThing; // 'not secret'

feature.sayPrivateThing(); 
// logs 'secret' and changes the value
// of privateThing</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>In the example above, we self-execute an anonymous function that
      returns an object. Inside of the function, we define some variables.
      Because the variables are defined inside of the function, we don't have
      access to them outside of the function unless we put them in the return
      object. This means that no code outside of the function has access to
      the <code>privateThing</code> variable or to the
      <code>changePrivateThing</code> function. However,
      <code>sayPrivateThing</code> does have access to
      <code>privateThing</code> and <code>changePrivateThing</code>, because
      both were defined in the same scope as
      <code>sayPrivateThing</code>.</para>

      <para>This pattern is powerful because, as you can gather from the
      variable names, it can give you private variables and functions while
      exposing a limited API consisting of the returned object's properties
      and methods.</para>

      <para>Below is a revised version of the previous example, showing how we
      could create the same feature using the module pattern while only
      exposing one public method of the module,
      <code>showItemByIndex()</code>.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using the module pattern for a jQuery feature</title>

        <programlisting>$(document).ready(function() {
    var feature = (function() {
        
        var $items = $('#myFeature li'),
            $container = $('&lt;div class="container"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;'),
            $currentItem,

            urlBase = '/foo.php?item=',
            
            createContainer = function() {
                var $i = $(this),
                    $c = $container.clone().appendTo($i);

                $i.data('container', $c);
            },
            
            buildUrl = function() {
                return urlBase + $currentItem.attr('id');
            },
            
            showItem = function() {
                var $currentItem = $(this);
                getContent(showContent);
            },
            
            showItemByIndex = function(idx) {
                $.proxy(showItem, $items.get(idx));
            },
            
            getContent = function(callback) {
                $currentItem.data('container').load(buildUrl(), callback);
            },
            
            showContent = function() {
                $currentItem.data('container').show();
                hideContent();
            },
            
            hideContent = function() {
                $currentItem.siblings()
                    .each(function() { 
                        $(this).data('container').hide(); 
                });
            };

        $items
            .each(createContainer)
            .click(showItem);
            
        return { showItemByIndex : showItemByIndex };
    })();
    
    feature.showItemByIndex(0);
});</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Inheritance</title>

    <para>Object literals and the module pattern, on their own, create only a
    single instance of the enclosed functionality. Sometimes essentially the
    same functionality exists several times throughout your code — for
    example, maybe there are a list of people on your page, and there is a set
    of behavior associated with each person. In these cases, you need a way to
    create multiple instances of a feature and to share code across similar
    features.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Prototypal Inheritance</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Classical Inheritance</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>It's Not All About the DOM</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Communication Between Components</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
