<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Exercises</title>

  <para>Each of these exercises uses the file
  <filename>/exercises/index.html</filename> included in the sample code. This
  file has the jQuery library included at the bottom of the page. For some
  exercises, you’ll be able to work directly in Firebug; for others, you will
  need to include other scripts after the jQuery script tag as directed in the
  individual exercises.</para>

  <para>In some cases, you will need to consult the jQuery documentation in
  order to complete an exercise, as we won’t have covered all of the relevant
  information in the lecture. This is by design; the jQuery library is large,
  and learning to find answers in the documentation is an important part of
  the process.</para>

  <para>Here are a few suggestions for tackling these problems:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>First, make sure you thoroughly understand the problem you're
      being asked to solve. Ask questions if the problem isn't clear.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Next, figure out which elements you'll need to access in order to
      solve the problem, and determine how you'll get those elements. Use
      Firebug to verify that you're getting the elements you're after.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Finally, figure out what you need to do with the elements to solve
      the problem. It can be helpful to write comments explaining what you're
      going to do before you try to write the code to do it.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Do not be afraid to make mistakes! Do not try to make your code
  perfect on the first try! Making mistakes and experimenting with solutions
  is part of learning the library, and you’ll be a better developer for it.
  Examples of solutions for these exercises are located in the
  <filename>/solutions</filename> directory in the sample code.</para>


  <xi:include href="exercises/selecting.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/traversing.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/manipulating.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/input-hint.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/reveal-hidden-text.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/tabbed-navigation.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/dropdown-menus.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/slideshow.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/load-external-content.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/load-json.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/sortable-plugin.xml" />
  <xi:include href="exercises/striping-plugin.xml" />
</chapter>
