<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Welcome</title>

  <para>jQuery is fast becoming a must-have skill for front-end developers.
  The purpose of this class is to give you an overview of the jQuery
  JavaScript library; at the end of the class, you should be able to complete
  basic tasks using jQuery, and have a solid basis from which to continue your
  learning.</para>

  <para>This book contains more information than we can possibly cover during
  the class, and so it is meant as a references more than a syllabus. You’re
  encouraged to continue working through the information and exercises once
  the class is complete if you want to broaden your knowledge of
  jQuery.</para>

  <para>This is a hands-on class. We will spend a bit of time covering a
  concept, and then you’ll have the chance to work on an exercise related to
  the concept. Some of the exercises may seem trivial; others may be downright
  daunting. In either case, there is no grade; the goal is simply to get you
  comfortable working your way through problems you’ll commonly be called upon
  to solve using jQuery. Example solutions to all of the exercises are
  included in the sample code.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Getting the Code</title>

    <para>The code we’ll be using in this book is hosted <link
    xlink:href="http://github.com/rmurphey/jqfundamentals">in a repository on
    Github</link>. You can download a .zip or .tar file of the code, then
    uncompress it to use it on your server. (If you’re git-inclined, you’re
    welcome to clone or fork the repository.)</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Software</title>

    <para>You'll want to have the following tools to make the most of the
    class:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Firefox browser</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Firebug extension for Firefox</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A plain text editor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For the Ajax portions: A local server (such as MAMP or WAMP), or
        an FTP or SSH client to access a remote server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Adding JavaScript to Your Page</title>

    <para>JavaScript can be included inline or by including an external file
    via a script tag. The order in which you include JavaScript is important:
    dependencies must be included before the script that depends on
    them.</para>

    <para>For the sake of page performance, JavaScript should be included as
    close to the end of your HTML as is practical. Multiple JavaScript files
    should be combined for production use.</para>

    <example>
      <title>An example of inline Javascript</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;script&gt;
console.log('hello');
&lt;/script&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>An example of including external JavaScript</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;script src='/js/jquery.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>JavaScript Debugging</title>

    <para>A debugging tool is essential for JavaScript development. Firefox
    provides a debugger via the Firebug extension; Safari and Chrome provide
    built-in consoles.</para>

    <para>Each console offers:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>single- and multi-line editors for experimenting with
        JavaScript</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>an inspector for looking at the generated source of your
        page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a Network or Resources view, to examine network requests</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>When you are writing JavaScript code, you can use the following
    methods to send messages to the console:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><command>console.log()</command> for sending general log
        messages</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>console.dir()</command> for logging a browseable
        object</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>console.warn()</command> for logging warnings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>console.error()</command> for logging error
        messages</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Other console methods are also available, though they may differ
    from one browser to another. The consoles also provide the ability to set
    break points and watch expressions in your code for debugging
    purposes.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conventions used in this book</title>

    <para>Methods that can be called on jQuery objects will be referred to as
    <code>$.fn.methodName</code>. Methods that exist in the jQuery namespace
    but that cannot be called on jQuery objects will be referred to as
    <code>$.methodName</code>.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Example of an example</title>

      <programlisting>// code examples will appear like this</programlisting>
    </example>

    <remark>Remarks about an example will appear like this.</remark>

    <note>
      <para>Notes about a topic will appear like this.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1/jquery.js">The
        jQuery source</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://api.jquery.com">jQuery
        documentation</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://forum.jquery.com/">jQuery
        forum</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="http://delicious.com/rdmey/jquery-class">Delicious
        bookmarks</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="http://docs.jquery.com/Discussion#Chat_.2F_IRC_Channel">#jquery
        IRC channel on Freenode</link></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
